<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the cathedrall church of Worcester vpon Sunday morning, Nouemb. 27. 1636 In the time of pestilence in other places of this land, and now published in the time of the visitation of that citie, with that grevious sicknesse, and by reason of it. By Geo. Stinton,</title>
            <author>Stinton, George, b. 1599 or 1600.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12977</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113491</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848725</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848725</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13838</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12977)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13838)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1694:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the cathedrall church of Worcester vpon Sunday morning, Nouemb. 27. 1636 In the time of pestilence in other places of this land, and now published in the time of the visitation of that citie, with that grevious sicknesse, and by reason of it. By Geo. Stinton,</title>
                  <author>Stinton, George, b. 1599 or 1600.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L. Lichfield, for H. C. [i.e. Cripps? or Curteyn?] Printer to the Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom[ini] 1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publishers' names suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13838:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN THE CATHEDRALL Church of <hi>Worceſter</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sunday Morning, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 27. 1636.</p>
            <p>IN The time of PESTILENCE in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places of this Land, and now publiſhed in the time of the Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that <hi>Citie,</hi> with that greivous Sickneſſe; and by reaſon of it.</p>
            <p>By GEO. STINTON,</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.8.</bibl> For my Brethren and Companions ſake I will wiſh th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Proſperity.</q>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by <hi>L. Lichfield,</hi> for <hi>H.C.</hi> Printer to the Vniverſity. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13838:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13838:2"/>
            <head>TO THE FAMOVS, ALTHOVGH NOW DEIECTED CITY OF WORCESTER,</head>
            <p>THE PLACE OF MY BIRTH and firſt breeding; and the dwelling place of many my good friends &amp; alliance, is this plain Sermon, ſince the Preaching reviſed and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified, in humble manner dedicated; Health and all Bleſſings wiſhed from the heart of the Author.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:13838:3"/>
            <bibl>1. KING. 8. <hi>v.</hi> 37.38.39</bibl>
            <q>If there be in the land Famine, if there be Peſtilence, Blaſting, Mil-dew, Locuſt, <hi>or</hi> if there be Caterpillars; if their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my beſiege them in the land of their ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, whatſoever Plague, whatſoever ſickneſſe <hi>there</hi> be,</q>
            <q>What prayer and ſupplication ſoever be made by any man, <hi>or</hi> by all thy people Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, which ſhall know every man the Plague of his owne heart, and spread forth his hands toward this houſe;</q>
            <q>Then heare thou in heaven thy dwelling place, and forgive!</q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13838:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ome forth, O ye daughters of Zion, and behold King Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> (ſaid King Solomon in his ſong chap: 3.11.) The daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Zion are the children and people of the Church: and unto you (Beloved) who are ſuch, give me leave to ſay, <hi>Come and behold King Solomon.</hi> I might beſpeake you as one of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's diſciples did him <hi>Mark,</hi> 13.1. to behold <hi>the</hi> goodly <hi>buildings of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> which King Solomon founded: that, if you pleaſe you may behold in the chap. next but one before this; but let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeake you to behold and looke over the excellent prayer which he made at the Dedication of that Temple, ſet down at large in this chap. and of which this my Text is part. King Solomon was a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, ſo he ſaith himſelfe: <hi>I the Preacher was King over Iſrael in Jeruſalem. Eccleſ.</hi> 1.12. That King over <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13838:4"/> was a Preacher. We have reaſon to love and like Preaching the better for his ſake. But I muſt tell you that the houſe which he built in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> was not to be called the houſe of Preaching, but the houſe of prayer.<note place="margin">Math. 12.41.</note> 
               <hi>It is written my houſe ſhall be called the houſe of prayer</hi> (ſaid <hi>a greater then Solomon</hi> of it. <hi>Math.</hi> 21.13.) and ſo <hi>Solomon</hi> made it; He as it were ſeaſoned it with prayer: and we may obſerve in this his prayer, how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten he ſpeaketh <hi>of prayer and ſupplication</hi> to be made in that houſe.<note place="margin">V. 30.33. &amp;c.</note> They were the words of <hi>S. Paul.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. <hi>I exhort that firſt of all ſupplications, prayers, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſions be made for all men.</hi> Firſt of all, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, before any thing elſe, in the very firſt place; which <hi>Solomon</hi> did in this place; and that <hi>for all men,</hi> as there ſhould bee occaſion, and when they ſhould be in any adverſity and affliction. When there ſhould <hi>be in the land Famine,</hi> occaſioned by <hi>Blaſting, Mil-dew, Locuſt, and Caterpiller,</hi> ſpoyling and devouring the graine and graſſe, and fruits of the ground; or by <hi>Enemies beſieging</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>in the land of their cities.</hi> When (I ſay) there ſhould <hi>be Famine,</hi> and Warre
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13838:4"/> 
               <hi>in the land,</hi> and that which is now in this land, <hi>Peſtilence, Plague, and ſickneſſe.</hi> Now, bleſſed be God for it, we may make an <hi>If</hi> of it, and ſay, <hi>Jf there be in the land fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, if there be blaſting, mil-dew &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>if</hi> there be <hi>Enemies beſieging</hi> &amp;c. for this our la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is peſtred with none of theſe. But we cannot fitly ſay, <hi>Jf there be Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Plague, and ſickneſſe:</hi> for we know and heare how it is in divers places of the land. And in this place, this city, we know what<note n="*" place="margin">The ſpotted fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the forerunner of a farre greater mortality this yeere.</note> 
               <hi>ſicknes</hi> hath been this yeare, and is ſtill, and taketh many of our good friends away. God Almighty who hath ſent theſe, ſend them away againe in his good time!</p>
            <p>And therefore now let me wave thoſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er, viz. <hi>Famine, Blaſting</hi> &amp;c. there being no occaſion of complaining of them; whereupon I may forbeare ſpeaking of them. Only we have reaſon to pray, that there may be no occaſion of complaining of any of them hereafter, as there is now of that other, <hi>the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence:</hi> by reaſon of which this text of mine is very ſeaſonable; I pray God make my ſermon upon it as profitable!</p>
            <p>Which Text, you ſee, is very large,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13838:5"/> and of which you perceive, that much might being made: and therefore you muſt give me leave with that Abbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viator of the Roman Hiſtory,<note place="margin">Rufus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us.</note> 
               <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſequi calculonum, qui ingentes ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas aeris brevioribus exprimunt:</hi> to doe as accountants uſe to doe, who make a few counters ſtand for great ſummes of coyne. In my preſent handling this Text, I ſhall pick out only a few things to pitch upon. And they are theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall ſpeak of that which occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the choice of it; <hi>Peſtilence in the land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, of that which hath occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>Peſtilence</hi> to be <hi>in the land:</hi> which I gather from the words, <hi>the Plague</hi> of a mans <hi>owne heart.</hi> The Plague of the hearts of men, I ſhall ſhew to bee the cauſe of the Plague in the land.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſhall ſhew what courſe is to be taken, when there <hi>is in the land Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Plague &amp;c.</hi> and that is twofold.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that <hi>every man</hi> ought to ſtudy to <hi>know the Plague of his owne heart.</hi> And next, that Gods <hi>people</hi> are to make <hi>prayer and ſupplication</hi> unto him <hi>in</hi> his <hi>houſe,</hi> and there to <hi>spread forth</hi> their <hi>hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13838:5"/>
            <p>This is all that I ſhall doe. And this while I ſhall doe briefly, and very plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I humbly crave Gods gracious aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It was the prediction of our bleſſed Saviour <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.7. <hi>there ſhall be Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in divers places.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> many times and fits of Peſtilence, many viſitations by it. And that prediction we know and ſee to be fulfilled. And here my obſervation is this, that when there are <hi>Peſtilences in divers places,</hi> the Lord is angry with thoſe places. In the Revelation of S. <hi>Iohn chap.</hi> 16.1.2. we read of <hi>the vials of the wrath of God,</hi> one of which being by an <hi>Angel powred upon the earth, there fell a noyſome and greivous ſore upon men,</hi> and <hi>the noyſome Pestilence.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> (As it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Pſ.</hi> 91.) <hi>This plague and grievous ſickneſſe</hi> (as we call it in our prayer) I may ſay is powred out of one of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of the wrath of God, by that deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Angel</hi> of whom we read 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.<note place="margin">Verſ. 16.</note> This the Lord himſelfe calleth one of his <hi>foure ſore judgements Ezek.</hi> 14.21. a ſore one indeed it may well be called, a noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and grievous ſore falling by it upon men (according to thoſe words in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13838:6"/> Revelation.) But to make what I ſaid, and that my obſervation more manifeſt. The words of my text are, <hi>If there be in the land Peſtilence.</hi> And the words of the Lord in the afore mentioned <hi>chapt.</hi> of <hi>Ezek. verſ.</hi> 19. are, <hi>Jf J ſend a Peſtilence into a land, and powre out my fury upon it.</hi> So that when the Lord ſendeth a Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence into a land, he then powreth out his fury upon it. The <hi>wrath</hi> of the Lord &amp; the Peſtilence, his <hi>anger &amp; fury,</hi> &amp; that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe going and being put together in the ſame Prophet <hi>chap.</hi> 7.14.15. and <hi>Ierem.</hi> 21.5.6. But you ſhall have further proofe from examples. In the 11. of <hi>Nu.</hi> 33. it is ſaid, that <hi>the wrath of the Lord was kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt the people, and the Lord ſmote the people with a very great plague.</hi> And chap. 16. 46. the words of <hi>Moyſes</hi> are, <hi>there is wrath gone out from the Lord; the Plague is begun.</hi> Again the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thoſe <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſaith thus, <hi>They provoked the Lord to anger with their own inventions, &amp; the Plague was great among them. Pſ.</hi> 106.29. Once more: 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.1. it is ſaid, that <hi>the anger of the Lord was kindled againſt Iſrael;</hi> and then, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. that <hi>the Lord ſent a Peſtilence upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13838:6"/> Jſrael.</hi> Hence you ſee that ſtill the Lord was angry when the Peſtilence was ſent abroad; and that this ſickneſſe hath beene a heavy conſequent of his heavy wrath and anger. And withall from the laſt ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted place that it is of his ſending, <hi>The Lord ſent a Peſtlence upon Iſrael.</hi> Even as before I told you the words of the Lord in <hi>Ezekiel, If J ſend a peſtilence into a land,</hi> and <hi>I have ſent among you the Peſtilence</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>Amos</hi> 4.10.) In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.16. it is ſaid, that <hi>he called for a Dearth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the land:</hi> and in like manner I may ſay, that he calleth for<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>in ſeptuag.</hi> for the Lord ſent a peſtilence 2. Sam. 24.15. Verſ. 9.</note> 
               <hi>a Death</hi> upon a land, and ſendeth it, biddeth it <hi>goe,</hi> and it <hi>goeth, come and</hi> it <hi>commeth, doe this, and</hi> it <hi>doth it</hi> (as the Centurion ſaid of himſelfe and his ſouldiours, <hi>Math.</hi> 8.) <hi>The ſtormy wind fulfilleth his word,</hi> Pſ. 148.8. and ſo doth the ſtormy winde (as I may call it) of ſickneſſe and death; which as it were bloweth us away, it ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filleth his word, his will and pleaſure. <hi>Before him went the Peſtilence</hi> (ſaid the Prophet <hi>Habakuk. chapt.</hi> 3.5.) it was ready at hand, when he would be pleaſ'd <hi>to call</hi> for it. And as it went before him, ſo it never went abroad but from him:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13838:7"/> making uſe of <hi>Labans</hi> words <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.50. I may ſay, that <hi>this thing proceedeth from the Lord.</hi> In the firſt of <hi>Samuel chap.</hi> 6.9. the Philiſtines being plagued with Emrods, the Prieſts and the diviners tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of <hi>a Chance</hi> that might <hi>happen</hi> unto them; <hi>Jf</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>the Arke of God go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not</hi> ſuch <hi>a way, then we ſhall know, that it is not his hand that ſmote us, it was a Chance that happened to us.</hi> But we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now plagued muſt know that it is not a chance that hath happened unto us, but that it is his hand that hath ſmitten us.<note place="margin">Verſ. 19.</note> As the Magicians of Egypt <hi>Exod.</hi> 8. ſaid of the duſt turned to lice, <hi>This is the finger of God:</hi> So may we ſay of the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, that this is the hand of God: and that we may perceive by the words of God himſelfe thus threatning <hi>Pharaoh, now I will ſtretch out mine hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that I may ſmite thee and thy people with Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence Exod.</hi> 9.15. And we know how <hi>David</hi> accounted of it when he made choice of it, ſaying, <hi>Let us fall now into the hand of the Lord.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.14. Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably in the laſt Proclamation for the Faſt, it is acknowledged &amp; pronounced to be <hi>the immediat ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of God.</hi> Yea, it is a ſword
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13838:7"/> in that hand, <hi>the ſword of the Lord, the Peſtilence,</hi> is the language 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.12. where is the ſame ſtorie with<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. Which <hi>ſword</hi> (to uſe the words of <hi>David.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.25. <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth one as well as another,</hi> as well rich as poore, young as old, where it lighteth and hitteth; and of which wee may ſay, as the ſame <hi>David</hi> did of <hi>the ſword of Saul,</hi> that <hi>from the blood of the ſlain it returneth not empty. Chap.</hi> 1.22. <hi>If</hi> I <hi>whet my glittering ſword, my ſword ſhall devour fleſh</hi> (ſaith the Lord, in the Song dictated unto <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 41.42.) Oh! what a world of fleſh hath this ſword devoured?<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.33.</note> How many <hi>Women</hi> (as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Agag</hi>) hath this <hi>ſword made childleſſe?</hi> In the holy ſtorie what doe we read of? <hi>fourteen thouſand and ſeven hundred Numb.</hi> 16.49. but there is a greater number in the ſame book, <hi>viz. twenty and foure thouſand Chap.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.8.</note> 25.9. and that (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) <hi>in one day.</hi> But we heare of a farre greater ſumme yet; even <hi>ſeventy thouſand men,</hi> and that in <hi>three dayes</hi> ſpace (ſome have thought leſſe then one day) 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.15. All theſe in all, <hi>a hundred and eight thouſand,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13838:8"/> and ſeven hundred,</hi> among the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Iſrael, as they are called in the Text. In the Hiſtories of other nations we find moſt ſtrange reports. To tell you ſome of them,<note place="margin">Pet. Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus. de fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>br. peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</note> and concerning ſome great ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. As <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice,</hi> in which in one plague time (as a learned Phyſitian hath repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) died <hi>ſexaginta medici,</hi> no fewer then threeſcore Phyſitians, who were not able to doe themſelves any good. And <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in which the Plague hath been very frequent, and is ſaid to have taken away a matter of two hundred thouſand in a yeere.<note place="margin">Henr. Blount. in his voyage into the Levant. pag. 44.</note> But the greateſt Plague that I ever heard of from one place, was that at <hi>Grand-Cairo</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in which not many yeeres ſince (as a late worthy Travailer who was told it there, hath told us) were ſwept away in one yeere eighteen hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred thouſand &amp; odde. And here I think upon that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of that mighty Perſian Emperour <hi>Xerxes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herodot. lib. 7.</note> who having gathered together as huge an army as (I think) ever before any had done, and having gotten to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen hundred thouſand ſtrong, view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon a time all that company, being together, broke forth into teares upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13838:8"/> this conſideration; that within the ſpace of one hundred yeeres not one man of ſo many hundred thouſand would be left alive,<note place="margin">Epiſt. lib. 3. ep. 7.</note> and (as <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith) <hi>quòd tot milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tam brevis immineret occaſus,</hi> ſo great a number ſhould laſt ſo litle a time. Vpon the conſideration of thoſe eighteene hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (one hundred thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d more then in that army) I cannot but ſay this; Good Lord! that in ſo ſhort a ſpace, not of one hundred, but of one yeere, not one man of ſo many hundred thouſand ſhould be left alive; and that ſo great a number in ſo litle time ſhould be cut of. To leave other countries, and to come home, to our own land, I cannot but here ſpeake of that moſt heavy and extreame plague in the twenty third yeere of <hi>King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the third AN. DOM. 1349. of which I may ſay as it is ſaid of <hi>the hayle in Aegypt, Exod.</hi> 9.24. that it was <hi>very grievous, ſuch as there was none like it in all</hi> this <hi>land, ſince it became a Nation.</hi> When (as the words of our Hiſtorian are) <hi>vix vivi potuerunt mortuos ſepelire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho: Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham.</note> there were hardly enow left alive to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the dead: and the opinon of many was, <hi>quòd vix decima pars hominum fuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13838:9"/> relitcta ad vitam,</hi> that ſcarce a tenth, one in ten of people was left alive. Iudge of it, by what I ſhall tell you out of our writers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but two or three places. And firſt of all our greateſt city (then not neere ſo great as now) <hi>London;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stow.</note> in which the Churches and Church-yards being ſo filled that they could receaue no more, a new burying place (there where now the great hoſpitall is) was purchaſed and hallowed,<note place="margin">The Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-houſe.</note> and therein more then fifty thouſand perſons laid and interred in the afore-named yeere. In which in another city, <hi>viz. Norwich,</hi> in the ſpace of ſixe moneths, even fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Ianuary</hi> the firſt, to the firſt of <hi>Iuly,</hi> the relation is, that there died fifty ſven thouſand a hundred &amp; four per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, beſides<note n="*" place="margin">In qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſdam Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligioſorum domibus, de viginti vix ſupere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum duo. Walſing. vid. Stow. in Annal.</note> religious perſons. And hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing told this of <hi>Norwich,</hi> let me tell this too of one Town in <hi>Norfolke, Yarmouth,</hi> in which is but one Church, &amp; yet at that time (as a Table hanging in that Church hath witneſſed) ſeven thouſand fifty and two were there taken away. But to come to later times, and freſher memory: let me ſpeake of London againe, and to ſay nothing of the preſent condition of it, of which we have weekely notice, give
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13838:9"/> me leave only to reflect upon that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall time there about an eleven yeares ſince, in which above twenty thouſand Families got them gone, <hi>eſcaping for their lives,</hi> (as <hi>the Angell</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Lot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> Gen. 19.) and (as it is ſaid of <hi>the Levite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> Iudg. 17.) <hi>departing to ſojourne where they could find a place.</hi> And yet notwithſtanding ſo many leaving that place, died of the Plague foure thouſand foure hundred threeſcore and three in one week. I here think of the words of <hi>Samſon,</hi> when he ſlew ſo many at one time, Iudg. 15.16. <hi>heaps upon heaps!</hi> At that time there were heaps of Carcaſſes one lying upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, like dead bones in a Charnel-houſe, and in that <hi>valley</hi> whither <hi>Ezekiel was carryed,</hi> chap. 37.1. Thus (beloved) you ſee how <hi>the Peſtilence,</hi> although it <hi>walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in darknes,</hi> yet it <hi>deſtroyeth in the noon-day,</hi> and then maketh <hi>thouſands, and ten thouſands</hi> to <hi>fall,</hi> Pſ. 91.6.7. It walketh in darkneſſe inviſibly, we cannot ſee the comming of it: like the Prince of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,<note place="margin">Verſ. 7.</note> Iob. 1. it <hi>walketh up and downe in the earth,</hi> from Citie to Citie, from place to place. It walketh (I ſay) yea more, it flyeth, it being <hi>the arrow that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13838:10"/> flyeth by day,</hi> as well as that <hi>walketh in darkneſſe,</hi> Pſ. 91.5. And that <hi>flying Rowle,</hi> which the Prophet <hi>Zacharie</hi> ſaw, chap. 5.1. and of which verſ. 3. thus <hi>ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, I will bring it forth, and it ſhall enter into the houſe of the thiefe, and into the houſe of him that ſweareth falſly by my name, and it ſhall remaine in the mid'ſt of his houſe, and ſhall conſume it.</hi> Many have been the houſes, and houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds, which this ſickneſſe, being once in the mid'ſt of them, hath conſumed. In the 12. chap. of <hi>Exodus</hi> v. 30. we read, that in that great ſlaughter, <hi>of the firſt borne in Egypt, there was not a houſe where there was not one dead.</hi> But we have heard of diverſe houſes infected, in which have been all dead, not one left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live. As the <hi>Egyptians</hi> at that time <hi>ſaid, we be all dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 33.</note> ſo haue had many in many houſes cauſe to ſay: for as the Lord threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by his Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> thus, chap. 6.9. <hi>It ſhall come to paſſe if there remaine ten men in one houſe, that they ſhall dye;</hi> ſo may I apply, and ſay, it hath come to paſſe, if there remained ten in one houſe, that they have all died. O the heavy hand! O the cruell ſword of God Almighty,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13838:10"/> and of his deſtroying Angell! O the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Arrowes</hi> of his quiver, <hi>the poyſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of drinketh up</hi> the <hi>spirits</hi> of men (to ſpeak with <hi>Iob,</hi> chap. 6.4.) Well might <hi>Moſes</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">V. 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>Pſ.</hi> 90. <hi>We conſume away in thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure,</hi> and <hi>when thou art angry all our dayes are gone:</hi> and fitly may we ſay <hi>Thou in thine indignation haſt ſtriken us with grievous ſickneſſe, and by and by,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the Pſalme in the booke for the faſt.</note> 
               <hi>we have fallen, as leaves beaten down with a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is now high time to ſtrike upon another ſtring, and to come unto what I propoſed in the ſecond place, <hi>viz.</hi> The cauſe of <hi>the Peſtilence in the land,</hi> which I ſaid, is <hi>the Plague of the hearts of men &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Marriners</hi> in <hi>Ionah,</hi> in that <hi>migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty tempeſt</hi> deſired to <hi>know for whoſe cauſe that evill was upon them, chap.</hi> 1.7. being perſwaded, although being heathens, that there was a cauſe for it extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And (Beloved) when ſuch an evill as this, <hi>malum poenae,</hi> an evill of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is upon us, it is good and fit to ſearch, that we may know for whoſe, and what cauſe it is. S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 11 30. told the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that <hi>among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13838:11"/> were weake, and ſickly,</hi> and that <hi>many ſlept,</hi> and dyed. But there is a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a cauſe for it; <hi>for this cauſe</hi> (ſaith he) namely, for their evill carryage, and condition when they came to <hi>the Lords Supper.</hi> When the Sonne of the Widdow of <hi>Zaraphath</hi> was dead, what were her words unto the Prophet? <hi>O thou man of God! art thou come to call my ſinne to remembrance, and to ſlay my ſonne?</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 17.18. Shee tooke her ſinne to be the cauſe of the death of her Sonne; and I may truely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that which ſhe ſpake of, to be the cauſe of the death, and ſlaughter of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſonnes of men. I may uſe the words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and moſt fitly ſay of <hi>the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot</hi> Sinne, that <hi>ſhe hath caſt downe many wounded, yea many ſtrong men have beene ſlaine by her. Prov.</hi> 7.26. It is worth the obſerving, what you may find, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 16. concerning that wicked king <hi>Zimri,</hi> who <hi>burnt a houſe over him</hi> ſelfe <hi>with fire and dyed:</hi> But what was the cauſe of ſuch his death? It is plainly ſaid there, that <hi>he dyed for his ſinnes which he ſinned,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 18.19. <hi>In the pot</hi> of ſinne <hi>there is death. Thou with rebukes doeſt chaſten man for ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 4.40.</note> 
               <hi>and makeſt his beauty to conſume a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13838:11"/> &amp;c.</hi> (ſaid <hi>David</hi> unto the Lord, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 39.12. And <hi>I will make thee ſick in ſmiting thee, in making thee deſolate becauſe of thy ſinnes,</hi> (ſaid the Lord, <hi>Micah.</hi> 6.13.) As the Lord anſwered <hi>David,</hi> when he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired concerning the three yeares fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; <hi>It is for Saul, and for his bloody houſe.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1: So if any enquire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this, and other yeares ſickneſſe, and mortality, and what may be the true cauſe of it, it may be anſwered in like manner: It is for ſinne, and for its bloody houſe: which bloody houſe, is that which my text ſpeaketh of, <hi>a mans owne heart,</hi> in which a mans ſpirituall part lyeth, and in which <hi>the Plague</hi> of ſinne hath its ſeat and reſidence. Of which part we may ſay moſt truely, what <hi>Tertullus</hi> did of S. <hi>Paul</hi> moſt maliciouſly, that <hi>we have found</hi> it to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Plague: Act.</hi> 24.5. And as S. <hi>Peter</hi> did of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> chap. 8.23. that <hi>we perceive</hi> it to be <hi>in the gall of bitterneſſe, and in the bond of iniquity.</hi> What bitter waters iſſue from this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, how much <hi>iniquity,</hi> and how many <hi>Plagues</hi> are in this part, <hi>the heart of man,</hi> our Saviour hath told us at large, whoſe words are, <hi>out of the heart of men, proceed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13838:12"/> evill thoughts, adulteries, fornications, murthers, thefts, covetouſneſſe, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, deceipt, laſciviouſneſſe, an evill eye, blaſphemy, pride, fooliſhneſſe,</hi> all which <hi>evill things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>defile</hi> and infect <hi>a man, Mark.</hi> 7.21.22.23. This is that <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward part,</hi> of which, ſpeaking to the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes,</hi> he ſaith, that it <hi>is full of ravening and wickedneſſe, Luk.</hi> 11.39. <hi>The heart of the ſonnes of men is full of evill, and madneſſe is in their heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 4.29.</note> (ſaith he who had <hi>ſo large a heart. Eccl.</hi> 9.3.) And how can it chuſe; when <hi>Satan</hi> many times <hi>filleth it,</hi> (as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ananias Act.</hi> 5.3.) this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>houſe, out of</hi> which <hi>the uncleane spirit came,</hi> and ſaid he would <hi>returne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to againe, entring in, and dwelling there,</hi> (according to our Saviours words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.) <hi>Satan</hi> thus filling it,<note place="margin">V. 44 45.</note> and that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirit dwelling in this houſe, it becommeth like the gyant <hi>Augaeus</hi> his ſtable, full of unſavoury matter, and as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith of the tongue, <hi>chapt.</hi> 3.8. <hi>an evill, full of deadly poyſon.</hi> Of the deadly poyſon and venome of ſinne, which <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth</hi> a man, yea <hi>undoeth</hi> him; and by reaſon of which many a man may cry out with the Prophet <hi>Jſai. ch.</hi> 6.5. &amp; ſay,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13838:12"/> 
               <hi>Wo is me, for I am undone; becauſe I am a man of uncleane lips, and J dwell in the middeſt of a people of uncleane lips!</hi> Sinne is <hi>the Plague of the heart,</hi> and the cauſe of <hi>the plague in the land.</hi> Men have had this plague in their hearts, the plague of pride and haughtineſſe: the plague of envie and malice: the plague of covetouſneſſe, and inordinate deſires: the plague of cruelty, of hypocriſie, and the like: They haue had it in their mouthes,<note place="margin">Luk. 6.45.</note> 
               <hi>speaking of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the heart,</hi> wiſhing a plague and peſtilence, one upon another; and now it is come home unto them, they have it in their houſes. I told you before the word of <hi>Tertullus</hi> the Oratour, calling S. <hi>Paul</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a plague:</hi> and I remember the words of that pander <hi>Sannio</hi> in the Comedie, ſaying of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Terent in Adelph.</note> 
               <hi>ego ſum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis,</hi> I am one that am a plague; and I may ſay that men have been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, plagues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting one another, with the plague, and contagion of ſinne; and now they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, plagues to one another, in infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another with the diſeaſe, and Contagio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the plague. Men have ſate <hi>in cathedra Peſtilentiae,</hi> in the chaire of Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, according to the phraſe in the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13838:13"/> Tranſlation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1. And now they ſit, <hi>in domo Peſtilentiae,</hi> in a Peſt-houſe. Men have kept ill company, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are now kept from company: Men have not feared God, and therefore God hath made men to feare men. Men have been ſick of ſinne,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.1.</note> and <hi>dead in it,</hi> and therefore are ſo many now ſick, and dead of this ſickneſſe. Our ſinnes which the Prophet <hi>Jſai. ch.</hi> 1.6. calleth <hi>putrifying ſores,</hi> have cauſed ſo many putrifying ſores to break out. Our <hi>ſinnes as red as ſcarlet,</hi> (according to the words of the ſame Prophet,<note place="margin">Verſ. 18.</note> in the ſame <hi>chapt.</hi>) have made the red, and ſcarlet ſpots ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Our proud fleſh hath cauſed the Lord to uſe this ſicknes as a corroſiue, to eat it away, and to make it eate, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>as doth a canker,</hi> or gangreene, (to uſe S. <hi>Pauls</hi> words in another caſe, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.<note place="margin">V. 17. Rom. 13.12. Pſal. 88.5.</note>) Our <hi>works of darkneſſe</hi> have brought among us <hi>the peſtilence that wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in darkneſſe,</hi> and which ſendeth ſo many to the <hi>place of darkneſſe.</hi> Our ſinnes haue increaſed, and therefore hath this diſeaſe increaſed. Heare, and think upon the words of the Lord unto <hi>Iſrael, Ierem.</hi> 30. <hi>J haue wounded thee with the wound
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13838:13"/> of an enemie, with the chaſtiſement of a cruell one; for the multitude of thine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: becauſe thy ſinnes were increaſed. v.</hi> 15. What ſhall I ſay? As <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 107.34. <hi>A fruitfull land the Lord maketh barren, for the wickednes of them that dwell therein:</hi> So may I ſay, a full Land, a full City, he maketh empty, for the wicknedneſſe of them that dwell therein. <hi>Behold the Lord maketh the earth empty, and maketh it waſt, and turneth it upſide-downe, and ſcattereth abroad the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof.</hi> &amp;c. and why? <hi>becauſe they have tranſgreſſed the lawes</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 24.1.5. To be briefe; as the Lord ſaith concerning <hi>Ieruſalem, Ezek.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Ye ſhall know that I have not done without cauſe, all that I have done in it:</hi> So muſt we know and be aſſured, that what he hath now done unto us, and in this Land, he hath not done without good cauſe: with which cauſe it is time to have done, and I have. Only as <hi>Quintilian</hi> having told of his many loſſes, ſaith thus;<note place="margin">Inſtitut. l. 6. in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aem.</note> 
               <hi>Non ſum am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitioſus in malis, nec augere lacrymaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas volo, uti nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſſet ratio minuendi!</hi> So let me ſay, I take no pleaſure here in ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravating this cauſe, or in making things
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13838:14"/> more or worſe, I wiſh rather there were cauſe for the contrary. The time paſſeth, and I now paſſe to the third thing, which I ſaid I would ſhew, <hi>viz.</hi> what courſe is to be taken when there is <hi>in the land Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, Plague,</hi> &amp;c. which I ſhall doe as briefly as I may.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of my laſt part I told you of the marriners in <hi>Ionah,</hi> how they deſired to <hi>know for whoſe cauſe</hi> that <hi>evill</hi> which they ſuffered was <hi>upon them:</hi> Let me now tell you other words of theirs unto <hi>Ionah, ver.</hi> 11. <hi>What ſhall we doe that the ſea may be calme unto us?</hi> In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner it concerneth us to talke of, and to take a courſe, to adviſe what is beſt to be done, and to doe our beſt, that the ſea (as I may ſay) of this ſickneſſe may be calme, the ſtorme of it be blown away, and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renitie enſue. And here let me turne you to an excellent place, then which, none ſitteth our turnes better; you have it <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, chap,</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 39.40.41. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>doth a living man complaine, a man for the puniſhment of his ſinnes? Let us ſearch and try our wayes: Let us lift up our hearts with our hands unto God, in the heavens.</hi> Living men whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13838:14"/> they are puniſhed, are apt to complaine,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.22.</note> and murmure, yea, to <hi>charg God fooliſhly,</hi> and with <hi>Jonah, to be angry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ch. 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>even unto death:</hi> but <hi>wherefore</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ieremie) doth a man ſo?</hi> he doth but ſuffer juſtly, it is but <hi>the puniſhment of his ſinnes.</hi> But to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine and murmure is not the way, and courſe to be taken; to doe ſo, will doe no good, but hurt: the beſt thing we can doe, is <hi>to ſearch and try our wayes: to lift up our heart, with our hands, unto God in the heavens.</hi> Which words you perceive how well they doe anſwer thoſe in my Text, and that which at the firſt I told you from them, when I obſerved the courſe, &amp;c. which, I told you is twofold.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that <hi>every man</hi> ought to ſtudy to <hi>know the Plague of his owne heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And next, that Gods <hi>people</hi> are <hi>to make prayers, and ſupplications</hi> unto him, in his <hi>houſe,</hi> &amp; there to <hi>ſpread forth</hi> their hands.</p>
            <p>Of which, one after the other, let me ſpeak. And here let me come in againe with the words of the Prophet <hi>Jeremie, let us ſearch and try our wayes:</hi> ſearch for <hi>the Plague of our own hearts,</hi> that we may <hi>know</hi> it, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid he did, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 77.6. <hi>I</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>commune with my owne heart,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13838:15"/> &amp; my ſpirit made diligent ſearch;</hi> &amp; as that woman did, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.8. <hi>who ſwept the houſe, &amp; ſought diligently</hi> for her <hi>loſt piece. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enena non deſunt ſed torpent,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi>) poyſon doth ſometimes lie ſtill, and as it were aſleep: and the plague, we know in ſome houſes lurketh, and lyeth dormant a great while before it breaketh out, and is plainly knowne: and ſo doth the plague of ſinne in the heart of man; which <hi>heart</hi> (ſaith the Lord <hi>Ierem,</hi> 17.9.) <hi>is deceitfull above all things, and desperat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wicked, who can know it?</hi> what man can know the heart of another man? and one man is loath that another ſhould know the deceitfulnes, and deſperate wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his heart. Even as wee have knowne ſome who have knowne the plague to have been in their houſes, and yet would not be knowne of it, would not acknowledge it till needs they muſt, being not able to ſmother it any longer. In like manner there are many who know <hi>a plague</hi> to be in their <hi>owne heart</hi> but they will not acknowledge it, like <hi>Gehazi,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 5, 25. and like <hi>Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Saphira, Act.</hi> 5.8. they <hi>cover their tranſgreſſions as Adam by hyding</hi> their <hi>iniquity in</hi> their <hi>boſome,</hi> to ſpeak with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13838:15"/> 
               <hi>Iob. ch.</hi> 31.33. even as it is ſaid of <hi>an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterous woman, Prov.</hi> 30, 20. that <hi>ſhee eateth, and wipeth her mouth, and ſaith, I have done no wickedneſſe.</hi> I ſaid before what the Lord ſaid concerning the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſſe and wickedneſſe of the heart <hi>Who can know it?</hi> but I may here ſay, who will know it? I meane that <hi>of his owne heart:</hi> that of another mans heart many are moſt willing to know, and with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> in <hi>Lucian</hi> they would faine have a window made that they might ſee and know it: But the deceitfulneſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate wickedneſſe, <hi>the Plague of his owne heart</hi> (I ſay) who will know it? Men might know it, if they did but take the care and courſe to know it; that that <hi>David</hi> did, whoſe words you heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>I commune with mine owne heart, and my spirit made diligent ſearch.</hi> Or if they would doe as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaid he did,<note place="margin">De Ira l. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> whoſe words are; <hi>quotidiè apud me cauſam dico, totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diem mecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcrutor, facta ac dicta mea remetior, nihil mihi ipſe abſcondo, nihil tranſeo.</hi> Every day I have a pleading with my ſelfe: when the day is paſſed, I exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min my ſelfe how I have paſſed it away; I repeat with my ſelfe all that I have
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13838:16"/> ſaid and done, I conceale nothing from my ſelfe, I leave nothing unthought of: and ſuch a courſe he that is a good and wiſe man indeed uſeth to take, as the Poet ſaith in his Character of ſuch a one <hi>Iudex ipſe ſui totum ſe explorat ad ungue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virgil</note> He Iudgeth, and ſearcheth, and ſifteth himſelfe throughly and perfectly. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! as the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſaith of <hi>Ephraim Ch.</hi> 7.9. <hi>gray haires are here and there upon him, yet he knoweth not:</hi> and as it is ſaid of <hi>the Church of Laodicea Revel.</hi> 3.17. that ſhee <hi>knew not</hi> that ſhee was <hi>wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and miſerable, and poore, and blind, and naked:</hi> So may it be ſaid of many that they will not know, will not be ſenſible of how it is with them, and of what is within them, <hi>the Plague of</hi> their <hi>owne hearts; Suis quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> malis blanditur:</hi> men are apt to ſooth themſelves in their evill waies: even as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaketh of <hi>the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly</hi> that <hi>he flattereth himſelfe in his own eyes. Pſ.</hi> 36.2. even as did that Church of Laodicea, of which I told you even now, who when ſhe was in that taking as you heard, yet ſaid, that ſhe was <hi>rich, and had need of nothing.</hi> It is a moſt true ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Seneca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epist.</hi> 116.</note> 
               <hi>Plerique ſtudent magis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſare
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13838:16"/> vitia quam excutere:</hi> it is the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of too many rather to excuſe, then to give over their vices: and it was the complaint of the Poet.</p>
            <q>Vt nemo in ſeſe tentat deſcendere nemo.<note place="margin">Perſ. ſat. 4.</note>
            </q>
            <p>No man goeth downe into himſelfe, no man ſoundeth the bottome of himſelfe; even as the Prophet Ieremy, ſpeaking of the wickedneſſe of the people, complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſaid, that he <hi>hearkned, but no man repented him of his wickedneſſe, ſaying, what have I done? Chap.</hi> 8.6. But enough of this, I will not inlarge upon theſe complaints. Having told you the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of one Poet, let me now tell you the counſel and adviſe of another—<hi>teipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Concute,<note place="margin">Horat. Serm. lib. 1. Sat. 3.</note> num qua tibi vitiorum inſeverit olim</l>
                  <l>Natura, aut etiam conſuetudo mala.</l>
               </q> Shake thy ſelfe, ſearch thy ſelfe whether or no nature, or evill cuſtome hath ſowen into thee any vices. Shake thy ſelf: doe as they doe who hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to doe with cloths and ſtuffe in infected houſes, who ſhake, and move, and ſtirre them, to get out of them the infection: or, as was injoyned to be done in a leprous houſe, which was <hi>to be ſcraped within round about, Levit.</hi> 14.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13838:17"/> 41. Search thy ſelf I ſay. <hi>Let us ſearch our wayes</hi> (once again to tell you the adviſe of the Prophet.) In the times of plague, we know there are ſearchers who have experience, and can judge of the diſeaſe: Let us (Beloved) be our own ſearchers, ſearchers of our ſelves, ſuch a one as <hi>David</hi> was, who ſaid (as I ſaid once and againe before) <hi>my spirit made diligent ſearch;</hi> &amp; ſearch he made about his <hi>heart, communing</hi> (as his words are) <hi>with</hi> his <hi>owne heart:</hi> by doing which he came to <hi>know the plague of his owne heart,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51.3. <hi>I acknowledge my faults, and my ſinne is ever before me,</hi> praying in that <hi>Pſalme</hi> thus, <hi>Create in me a clean heart O God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 10.</note> He knew his heart had been foule, and had need of clenſing, and therefore prayed for it, <hi>Purge me with hyſope, and J ſhal be clean, waſh me</hi> &amp;c. <hi>waſh me through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from mine iniquity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 7. 2. Pſ. 19.12.</note> 
               <hi>and cleanſe me from my ſinne. O cleanſe thou me from my ſecret faults.</hi> But to make ſhort: Let my exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation be that of the Prophet <hi>Jſai. ch.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. <hi>Waſh yee, make you clean, put away the evill of your doings,</hi> and that of S. <hi>Iames ch.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Cleanſe your hands, you ſinners and purifie your hearts yee double minded</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13838:17"/> and to make uſe of the words, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.43. <hi>Let us remember our wayes, and all</hi> our <hi>doings, wherein we have been defiled, and lothe</hi> our <hi>ſelves in our owne ſight, for all</hi> our <hi>evils that</hi> we <hi>have committed!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is one thinge more you know which I muſt needs ſay ſomthing of, but now can ſay but litle, which is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>prayer and ſupplication</hi> to be <hi>made</hi> by Gods <hi>people.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>They are the words of S. <hi>Iames,</hi> in his laſt <hi>chap.</hi> 14. <hi>Is any ſick among you? Let him call for the Elders of the Church, and let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pray over him.</hi> Is any infectious &amp; contagious ſicknes among us? Let me ſay too, let the Elders of the Church, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, be called unto, and upon, and they muſt pray for the people: according to the adviſe, <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2.16.17. (being part of the Epiſtle for the Faſt-day.) <hi>Gather the people, aſſemble the Elders, let the Prieſts, the Miniſters of the Lord, weep between the porch, and the Altar, and let them ſay; Spare thy people O Lord &amp;c.</hi> and as <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh called for Moſes, and Aaron,</hi> who were Prieſts, (for <hi>Moſes and Aaron a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Prieſts, Pſ.</hi> 99.6. <hi>and ſaid intreat the Lord your God that he may take away
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13838:18"/> from me this death, Exod.</hi> 10.16.17: So it is the part and duty of the Prieſts, and Miniſters eſpecially, to intreat the Lord God, that he would take away from the people this death and Plague; and this they muſt doe, according to my Text, in his <hi>houſe,</hi> his <hi>holy places,</hi> and Temples. As <hi>David</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſ. 68.33.</note> 
               <hi>Pſ.</hi> 42.8. that he <hi>went with the multitude into the houſe of God,</hi> ſo the Prieſt and multitude of people, who are ſafe and free, muſt goe together into the houſe of God, and there <hi>make prayer and ſupplication unto him;</hi> they muſt, as the ſame <hi>David</hi> ſaid, that he, and the people would doe, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 132.7. <hi>goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Tabernacle, and fall low on</hi> their <hi>knees before his footſtoole,</hi> and withall (according to my Text) <hi>spread forth</hi> their <hi>hands</hi> there, and as the ſame <hi>David</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 134 2. <hi>lift up</hi> their <hi>hands in the Sanctuary:</hi> their hands, as <hi>Davids</hi> were,<note place="margin">V. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Pſ.</hi> 26. being <hi>waſhed in Innocency,</hi> before they with him <hi>goe to the Lords Altar,</hi> and with thoſe hands the heart being lifted up, according to the words formerly cited, <hi>Let us lift up our hearts with our hands unto God in the heavens,</hi> and thus with <hi>David, Pſ.</hi> 5. <hi>comming into</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:13838:18"/> Gods houſe <hi>upon the multitude of</hi> his <hi>mercies, &amp; in</hi> his <hi>feare worſhiping towards</hi> his <hi>holy Temple,</hi> both Prieſt &amp; people may ſay with him, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 48.8. <hi>We wait for thy loving kindneſſe (O God) in the mid'st of thy Temple:</hi> and they may hope and be confident, that although (as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 11.4.) <hi>the Lords ſeat is in heaven,</hi> yet with all (as it is there) <hi>the Lord is in his holy Temple,</hi> that this Lord will (as the ſame <hi>David</hi> was aſſured he would his, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 18.6.) <hi>heare</hi> their <hi>voyce out of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Temple,</hi> and that their <hi>complaint ſhall come before him, and ſhall enter even into his eares,</hi> and that (according unto the prayer of <hi>Solomon, Davids</hi> ſonne in my Text) he will <hi>heare in heaven his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place, and forgive.</hi> And as there muſt be publique prayer in Gods houſe, ſo ought there to be private in our owne, and in our private roomes, according to our Saviours adviſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Enter into thy chamber, and when thou haſt ſhut thy doore, pray to thy Father which is in ſecret,</hi> and according to the example of <hi>Daniel,</hi> who in his <hi>chamber, kneeled upon his knees three times a day and prayed. Dan.</hi> 6.10. Both publique and private prayer are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13838:19"/> now injoyned by our <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> and I truſt it will prove a <hi>ſoveraigne</hi> remedie for the occaſion. Let me be bold and ſay, making uſe of our Saviours words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.21. <hi>This kind,</hi> this kind of ſickneſſe <hi>will not goe out</hi> of this land, <hi>but by prayer and faſting.</hi> We know what hath been the effect of <hi>prayer and ſupplication,</hi> and that at ſuch a time as this. <hi>The Lord</hi> threatned to <hi>ſmite</hi> his people <hi>with the Peſtilence, Moſes beſought</hi> him to <hi>pardon</hi> their <hi>iniquity,</hi> and <hi>the Lord</hi> preſently <hi>ſaid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 12.19.20,</note> 
               <hi>J bave pardoned according to thy word. Numb.</hi> 14. The Lord did ſmite them with the Peſtilence, but when <hi>Phineas ſtood up and prayed, the plague ceaſed.</hi> (As we uſe to read it, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 106.30. In that great Plague, <hi>in the time of King David, David and the Elders of Iſrael fell upon their faces,</hi> and <hi>prayed</hi> for the <hi>people, and called upon the Lord, and the Lord commanded the Angell, and he put up his ſword againe into the ſheath thereof,</hi> (as wee may read 1 <hi>Chron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 16.17.26.27. 2. King. 20.7.</note> 21.) Once more, <hi>King Hezekiah was ſicke</hi> (as it is thought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and is probable) of the plague, and <hi>ſicke to the death,</hi> and he <hi>prayed unto the Lord, and hee ſpake unto him, and hee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13838:19"/> gave him a ſigne</hi> (as it is 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.24. And as we ſee hence what hath been the effect of prayer at ſuch a time as this, ſo we are told what it ſhall be, and that by the Lord himſelfe, and that too, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this very petition of <hi>Solomon,</hi> which is my text: unto which you will finde the Lords gracious anſwer, in the laſt mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned booke 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 7. <hi>The Lord appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſaid to Solomon, J have heard thy prayer, and if I ſend Peſtilence among my people, if my people which is called by my name ſhall humble themſelves, and pray, and ſeeke my face and turne from their wicked waeyes; then I will heare from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and will forgive their ſinne, and will heale their land, v.</hi> 12.13.14 &amp; from this Lord, his Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> hath aſſured us that upon the humiliation of the people, upon the teares and Prayer of <hi>the prieſts, the Lord will be jealous for his land, and pity his people, chap.</hi> 2 17.18. and <hi>the prayer of faith</hi> of Gods faithfull people <hi>ſhall ſave the ſicke, and the Lord ſhall raiſe him up</hi> &amp;c. (ſaith <hi>S. Iames chapt.</hi> 5.15.) and therefore (as he ſaith <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.) <hi>Is any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you afflicted? Let him pray.</hi> And let me ſay for thoſe among us that are affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13838:20"/> let us pray; for it may be the caſe is ſo with ſome of them that they cannot pray for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves. <hi>Pray for one another, that yee may bee healed.</hi> (Saith the ſame Apoſtle in the ſame <hi>chapt. verſ.</hi> 16.) It is the beſt office that one Chriſtian can doe for another, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently and earneſtly deſired might bee done for him; and at the hands of thoſe unto whom he wrot, begg'd for nothing more earneſtly then for that, as doe ſhew thoſe words of his unto the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, <hi>Now I beſeech you brethren, for the Lord Ieſus Chriſts ſake, and for the love of the spirit, that yee ſtrive together with me in your prayers to God for me! chapt.</hi> 15.30. And therefore, as he ſaid unto the Hebrewes, <hi>chap.</hi> 13, 19. <hi>I beſeech you to doe this:</hi> ſo let me beſeech that this may bee done, frequently, faithfully, humbly, heartily. Pray for thy ſelfe out of great neceſſity; For others out of Chriſtian charity. Pray that thou maiſt truly <hi>know the Plague of</hi> thine <hi>owne heart:</hi> that God would ceaſe it, in thy heart: and that he would ceaſe and ſtop it in the land. Vſe the prayer of the prophet <hi>Habbakuk,</hi> in that <hi>chapt.</hi> where he ſpeaketh of the Peſtilence, <hi>ch.</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:13838:20"/> 3.2. <hi>O Lord in wrarth remember mercy!</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 5.</note> that of the prophet <hi>Iſai, chapt.</hi> 64.9. <hi>Be not wrath very ſore, O Lord, neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member iniquity for ever! behold, ſee, wee beſeech thee, we are all thy people!</hi> That of the prophet <hi>Daniel, chapt.</hi> 9.19. <hi>O Lord heare, O Lord forgive, O Lord hearken and doe not deferre for thine owne ſake, O God! Or that of Solomon in my text, Heare thou in heaven thy dwelling place and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give!</hi> pray, that God would heare in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, his <hi>dwelling place,</hi> the prayers her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> made upon <hi>Earth,</hi> his <hi>footstoole:</hi> and that he would heare in heaven the prayers made in heaven for us upon the earth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Ieſus Chriſt our Mediatour, <hi>who ever li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>veth to make interceſſion for us;</hi> By th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bleſſed Saints, out of the altitude of their charity, the Church triumphant for the Church militant; By <hi>the ſoules under the Altar, who cry, and ſay, how long O Lord holy and true, O thou that heareſt the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers unto thee ſhall all fleſh come.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him <hi>that heareth the prayers,</hi> God the Father; to Ieſus Chriſt, God the Sonne, who prayeth for us; and to God the holy Ghoſt, be all Honour, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13838:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
